[SPEAKER_01]: Practical side of it being what?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of the time, when practice is talked about, it's just sort of talked about and sort of entertained as a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But on a day-to-day sort of living of dhamma, then it's sort of like... it's very easy to revert to keeping things in an unannounced length.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's the... that's like the... Hey, Dalia.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it needs to be recognized even before you become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that the dhamma, in order to be done properly, requires a great deal of giving up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, theoretically, a lay person can practice the dhamma, but from the dhamma point of view, lay life, it's already a compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a compromise for somebody who is unaware of the dhamma, and unaware of the requirements, and unaware of what the practice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for somebody who is aware of it, who kind of got the idea, and then chooses to stay a layman, that's a compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly already the beginning of keeping the dhamma at the arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you know where the dhamma should apply,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, for whatever reasons, personal, you refuse to go in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you choose to focus then on the suttas and the instances where the Buddha sort of did successfully enable the right view in lay people.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, so I don't have to be a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to give up
[SPEAKER_00]: My existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to give up familiarity of my environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to give up my family, and I can get the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, those people were far, far less in number back in the Buddha's day.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like lay people who became sotāpannas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mostly it was monks and nuns.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no instance of a lay person being an anārahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's impossible to live that life.
[SPEAKER_00]: With a full enlightened mind, the environment, the values, the whole thing, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it always boils down to this kind of your actions and your choices and lack of transparency in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's obvious, not everybody can be a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, everybody is perfectly capable of not avoiding responsibility for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the lack of transparency.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's mostly where I was getting at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, even when you do commit, it's, after a while, it's very easy to feel fully justified to be... Oh, yeah, because becoming a monk
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a necessary step towards creating the circumstances for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not... doesn't mean automatically you're practicing by becoming a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: And yeah, that's another thing sometimes people need to realize.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think, oh, if only I'll become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all I need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then I'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, not at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're still a layman, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless you become a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Between a layman and a member of the saṅgha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you wearing brown cloth wrapped around you is just a new fashion statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, look, I'm this.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is my set of values.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a necessary statement, more often than not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't mean you arrive at clarity, transparency and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to always keep the reasons for becoming a monk in the first place, keep it in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did you want to become a monk?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you free from suffering simply by becoming a monk?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so now you can actually practice further.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's when people forget that, that's when, you know, you becoming a monk becomes more like a career, socially oriented purposes and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is all nice in the worldly manner, but it's a... it's a layman's undertaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if, you know, if somebody, like, doesn't want to practice dharma, chooses to be a layman, that's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can't... Well, you can't complain about anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's a different topic.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's... the problem is when... when you know the value of the dhamma,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what it entails, at least to an extent, but then you choose to justify not doing it because, you know, you need to be a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's a compromise.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you kind of disqualify yourself from proper understanding of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you say, like, keep an eye out for your anxieties?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good way to...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, keep an eye for the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of these acts of covering things up from yourself, it's to cover up the responsibility, because it's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If by some miracle responsibility would be felt pleasantly, nobody would be covering it, and everybody would automatically go towards arahantship, towards full enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Responsibility is not pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never was, never will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was never a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is you not being able to endure that discomfort and habitually looking away from it, giving in to distracting yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you do it, the more dependent you become on doing it, doing that avoidance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That sort of meant like... using anxiety as a criteria?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Using anxiety as a criteria is another way of saying using... discerning the liability to suffering as a criteria.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't matter if you're a layman, doesn't matter if you're a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: What matters is, are you still liable to suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's virtually inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Liability to suffering, it's virtually inseparable from being a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, by proxy then, if you really want to commit to free yourself from suffering, you have to recognize you need to commit to changing your environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot live in the world around... that's fully based upon values of sensuality, family, company, distraction, desires, lack of restraint, and somehow go beyond that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, you can say, oh, it's not my fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I'm not a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't be a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can say it's not my fault that I have to be a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is your fault that you're still liable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter what you are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your fault is whether you're liable to suffering or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because suffering is nothing to do with any external circumstance whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you suffer, it's because there is craving in your mind, not in the things that made you suffer, seemingly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's something you're always responsible for.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if, as a rule of thumb, you avoid responsibility for even things that are not so deeply rooted, you're not going to see this.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you start accepting responsibility for everything else, in order to... in order to be able to see it on this level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, being a monk is basically... it gives you a sort of a better environment, better focus.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, not by default.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still need to exercise certain, you know, reasoned decisions, because, you know, some of the monasteries are simply not suitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of the places are not suitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not being a monk in any tradition is not suitable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be a monk, and people will think it's the same Buddhist monk in the tradition that doesn't keep vinaya, that simply doesn't have the precepts, or has completely different precepts that are not on the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to be... and I'm not saying like only to be in the right tradition, but you need to be in the right set of values, which means you need to know the set of values, and you read the suttas, and you get the set of values.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yes, you have like Theravāda monks, which is what we are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many of them would not keep the rules that you're supposed to keep.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's just how things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't mean like a whole Theravāda... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: People individually choose to not adhere, not adhere to rules or things that they know should be adhered to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can still choose to go to that tradition or some like other tradition that doesn't necessarily keep those rules, but then you can keep those rules, if you can.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you think that the environment will prevent you from keeping rules, because of, you know, what people would expect from you and so on, then you shouldn't be going into that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I mean, ordaining in a Theravāda tradition, but in some temple monastery, that it's all about, like, you know, money and events and so on, well, that's not something you would want to do if you want to practice dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, precepts are a personal choice, a personal commitment, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, again, comes through that recognition of personal responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no commandment that demands from you to do it, but if you want to practice the dhamma, there are necessary bases for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's cheap.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be more honest if you say, I don't want to practice dhamma and I'll go and sort of not keep the precepts, than saying, I am practicing the dhamma and I don't need to keep the precepts, which is what you hear people relatively often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, you don't need to give up your lay life, you don't need to give up sensuality, and you can be enlightened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not according to the Buddha, which, ironically, you profess to follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, today many things, vastly different things, are called Buddhism, but it doesn't mean that the Buddha was teaching all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... if you wonder, so how do I know what the Buddha was teaching?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't know a hundred percent, because he's long gone, but you can certainly know what is least likely to be wrong, in terms of the teachings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can know what is most likely closest to what he's been teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: What all the traditions agree were the earliest texts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how, okay, so this is my starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not perfect.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be perfect, because it's been two and a half millennia since.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this is my starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll start investigating this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not like, I'll pick and choose that which will suit my already predetermined lifestyle that I do not want to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I'm too afraid.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'll know that you're covering something up,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you get emotionally disturbed on account of encountering the opposing view, if somebody says, you should... it's your duty to give up the lay life, and if you feel affected by that, or get angry with the person who said it, on top of that, you're covering things up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you're a layman or because you're not a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you're avoiding responsibility for what you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's hard not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why you are in that environment, in that setup.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think that those days before, as a layperson myself, when I started reading the suttas, that, fortunately, became very clear to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha outline says that the only thing that matters in the world is suffering and freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever you do, it's on account of how you feel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either to prolong pleasure, because not enough pleasure is suffering, or to avoid pain, because enduring pain is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he says, and this is the way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come and see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I remember reading that, and it was obvious.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to give up the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, you know, there is suffering, there is the way out, you can follow it, but you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not literally that I will be, like, enduring the eternal damnation if I don't become a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, at the same time, I felt, oh, so now I'm responsible.
[SPEAKER_00]: For better, I go forth and become a monk and pursue this freedom from suffering that the Buddha teaches.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm equally responsible for not doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I choose to stay a layman,
[SPEAKER_00]: I cannot complain for whatever happens to me for the rest of my life and future, whatever, wherever your beliefs were.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you might not be responsible for particular things, good or bad, that happen to you, but you're responsible for choosing to stay in the environment where these things can happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Environment being saṃsāra, fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I thought, okay, so that's... it's quite an obvious choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obviously, for me, it was a no-brainer choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because really, like, the only... the only way you could stay in the environment that makes you liable, pressured by feelings, good or bad, doesn't matter, is to ignore that, that you are then liable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which I couldn't ignore, because the choice became very clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, becoming a monk felt like... not like a... some, you know, mystical duty that I need to do to be saved.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just felt like, oh, it's just a step towards this right direction of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just a step towards the environment that can provide me with better conditions for practice, more efficient practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because most of the lay life, even if the one... if you want to practice the dhamma, would... most of your energy would be spent just sort of fending off
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality and ill-will, and company, and crowd, and bombardment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's no... there's no way you would, on top of that, then you'll make all the amount of... necessary amount of effort to actually discern through that muck and swamp of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, if you don't spend most of your time just fending off things, then, yeah, you will have enough effort built up to start looking through things and... and deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When people don't want to leave that sensuality and... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, and the only reason you wouldn't want to leave sensuality is because you still avoid responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to leave it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you have to do is stop ignoring the fact that you are responsible for staying there.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people say, yeah, oh, you're so lucky you can be a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I'm... or we are lucky inasmuch we are still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having been, like, riddled with sickness and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there is luck.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's often pure chance.
[SPEAKER_00]: A bit, you know, maybe we're a bit careful, make sure you kind of, you know, use your body, don't get indolent and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, overall, that's as far as the luck goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything else is based on the choices monks individually made.
[SPEAKER_00]: I didn't, like, wake up one morning and suddenly became a fully ordained monk.
No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You had to leave the home, you had to leave the family, the, you know, the people you were involved, you had to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means it can never be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you recognize responsibility, you recognize the value of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just when you ignore that, then you just try to keep it, as you said, at the arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are lucky you're a monk and I'm unlucky.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, none of us is responsible for our own situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or when people say, oh, I can't be a monk now because I have the family to look after.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that is true.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the reason you can't be a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why do you have a family that you have to look after?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was that just such a magically thrown upon you?
[SPEAKER_00]: You just woke up one morning with six children you had to look after?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You each time, individually, chose that to engage in a full-on sensual acts that result in children, sometimes planned or unplanned, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot happen accidentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now you have to look after the consequences of your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's exactly what saṃsāra is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, so what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: What you do is stop ignoring responsibility for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you'll know whether you really want to be a monk or you're fine by staying a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll never be clear on that for as long as you ignore responsibility for the situation you're already in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, say, someone wants to go forth or even to get a taste of, while staying a layman, what he or she should do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you know precepts, like, what precepts entail before you commit to them?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you, like, this is the results I'll have.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can know them in terms of... you can know where they are and what they require you to abstain from and practice and be mindful of, but until you start doing it, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, it's like asking, can you feel the heat of the fire that you would have lit up with these wet sticks if they were dry?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can know that there will be a heat as a result of the fire, but you can't feel that heat for as long as you don't dry the sticks.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as long as you don't dry out your behavior of greed, aversion, delusion, conceit and everything else, you can't feel the heat of the dhamma in terms of that wisdom and that liberation from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to commit to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to keep the precepts in order for your mind to start drying out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the wisdom can take place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot foresee what's the... You can foresee on the abstract level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The heat will probably be the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, what that heat is, or how it's felt, and how it's experienced, you don't know, because your sticks were always wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might choose, then, that whatever your family, your committee, your job, is more important to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, rather, having the insecurity from giving these things up, is something you don't want.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, on account of it, you say, well, this dhamma is all good, but, you know, I like being being a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's absolutely fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as you don't use that to at the same time cover up responsibility for that very choice, that's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't cover up the responsibility for that very choice, now you will feel responsible for not following the way out of suffering, for staying in the environment that provides you with pleasure you are familiar with, and provides you also with possibilities of suffering that you have to deal with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then endure that responsibility of that choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's actually what the Buddha was teaching to lay people.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't say you should all become monks and nuns.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said you should all be aware that you are the owners of your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: The burden of your choice is always on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, choose wisely, choose skillfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still, even as a layman, choose according to the five precepts, as in not out of greed, aversion, delusion, don't harm others.
[SPEAKER_00]: All these things, because it's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the worst thing, basically, is ignoring the responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where ignorance comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the root of everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You said, like, eh... familiarity.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... earlier, that, eh... the simile you gave, like, you always had wet sticks.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know anything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know anything else, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you have a degree of faith, initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: To, like, recognize, abstractly, that, yeah, if the sticks dry out, it's more... greater likelihood that they'll light a fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now I just have to endure for as long as it takes for them to dry out, and maybe, you know, don't jump back into the water, because that was my familiar environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it will stop being your familiar environment, and the sense restraint will become your familiar environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it will require your effort not to restrain, but to go back to centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you know you're on the right path.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason, like, giving things up, keeping precepts, accepting responsibility is unpleasant, is because you keep avoiding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You always have been avoiding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, someone hears this, eh... starts with the sensual strain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hm.
[SPEAKER_01]: What next?
[SPEAKER_01]: How... how do you like that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, we're still talking about the... the layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even a monk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start with a sense restraint as a necessary basis for understanding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the next step is then to start contemplating things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do you want to understand the dhamma?
[SPEAKER_01]: To end suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: To not suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: To not suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now, on the basis of sense restraint,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you haven't been engaging with sensuality, haven't been giving into your will, expression of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is your suffering there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, eh... let's say, you don't know, like... all your life, all you knew was sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you realize...
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, think of it like this, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, you want something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have a sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you restrain yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's felt unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: The feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: The feeling of displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it unpleasant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, well, it's pressuring.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is pressure, left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why is this pressure felt unpleasantly by you?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it because you said no to yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: You would want to jump at that sort of a conclusion, but not really.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why is it then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can say yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you said no to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the most obvious answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why did you say no to yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Was there nothing?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, suddenly, you just said no to yourself, and pain arisen as a direct result of saying no to yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or was there something before you said no to yourself, to which you said no?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I had to have something to say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, your pain started before you said no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You saying no was not the first point of that whole experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, when you... like, if saying no is where the pain is, means anytime you say no, it will be felt painfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I offer you this poisonous drink, to drink it, they will cause you pain for weeks, and you say no to it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you suffer on account of that, or would you be elated and happy on account of that very no?
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be elated and happy, because the basis for saying no is what determines whether it's felt pleasantly or unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, when you say no to your sensual desire, and you suffer on account of it, that pain is in sensual desire, and saying no reveals the pain that started with sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: If sensual desire were truly pleasant, as I said that many times before, you wouldn't feel pressured towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If sensual desire were pleasant, you wouldn't need to act out of it, because desire in itself would be bliss.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual desire means you need to act, and get, and obtain, and maintain, and protect, and engage with it more, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means,
[SPEAKER_00]: It touches you painfully and you want to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's always the first and always the the the main framework for any engagement with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter the pleasure you can get secondarily from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always rooted first in trying to avoid the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sense restraint can never be the reason for neither pain nor pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abstaining from action cannot be the reason for pain nor pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can only reveal the reason for pain or pleasure that's already implied in the action you're restraining from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you're already committing to saying no, not seeing... you're saying no to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, initially, you're going to blame your sense restraint for your pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as I said, if that were always... if that were truly the case, means sense... means saying no to your senses would always be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying no to the harmful exposure of the senses is felt pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's felt, oh, God, I dodged a bullet there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same act of saying, saying no to, I refuse this sight, I refuse this taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when you feel the pain of sensory strain, stop misidentifying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only stop misidentifying it, if you started practicing sensory strain first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what you should do, once you start practicing sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Start seeing that the pain is not in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The pain is that which you're restraining yourself from.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how long do you have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no prescription.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said himself, sometimes half a night is enough, sometimes...
[SPEAKER_00]: You maybe need to do a full day, something, seven days, seven months, seven years.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the point is, if you're doing it like this, the results will have to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: You cannot be doing it rightly without the right results.
[SPEAKER_00]: Results that are freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another thing you should factor in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you need to be patient to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, at the same time, don't pretend, don't think like, oh, so there's ever, never any verifiable result for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just need to do this out of faith and there is nothing to be attained anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there is.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a lot to be attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're not attaining it, it's because you're not doing things rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: As simple as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't believe me, well, read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: On many occasions they would have said, in many different ways, but always the best simile was the hen sitting on her eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if the hen wishes,
[SPEAKER_00]: May I be enlightened, or may my chicks pierce out safely into this world from these shells.
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't, because she's not sitting on the eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if the monk wishes, may I reach enlightenment, he won't, because he's not doing the right practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the other hen, she sits on her eggs, and even if she doesn't wish, may my chicks pierce out the shell safely and come into this world, they will, because she's sitting on the eggs.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the
[SPEAKER_00]: Similarly, if the monk is doing the practice correctly, even if he doesn't wish, may my mind be purified from greed, urge and delusion, may I stop being liable to suffering, he will, because he's doing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you hear people saying there's nothing to be attained, it's because they haven't attained anything and they're covering it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's nothing to be attained, why does every... virtually every sutta talks about attainments?
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, having desire for attainments is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people don't want this pleasure on account of their dhamma practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: They want soft, inspirational, poetic words.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will make them feel good, not feel bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's literally like you go to the doctor and you ask for the cure and he says, yeah, it's bitter, it's gonna make you vomit, have diarrhea, wet your bed, torture you, but it will cure you and then you'll be fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, but I don't want all the side effects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you just continue pretending you're not ill.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think, that's where he started, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, being practical.
[SPEAKER_01]: Giving you the arm's length, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's what I mean, like, you can... you won't even see the value of being practical and clear in understanding and the meaning, for as long as you're avoiding your own personal responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to stop all the responsibility for what you choose to be, to do, to attend.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you get a better picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you'll be unable to ignore as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as I said, yeah, wanting to be free from suffering is yet another desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as the Buddha said, it's the desire that can then start directing you
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards finding out what the dhamma is, which will then eventually result in freedom from desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's desire, that will eventually cancel all the other desire, including itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what Buddha meant when he said, desire is to be abandoned by the means of desire, and craving is to be abandoned by the means of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You crave for liberation from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And craving is suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because of craving for liberation, not craving for sensuality and everything else, you actually get to make the effort, discern, layer by layer, what liberation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by doing so, you free yourself from the very craving that made you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a good craving and bad craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good craving will cancel itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bad craving will perpetuate itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't see either, if you keep avoiding and turning a blind eye to the responsibility of your actions, and your situation, and your choices, and all the results that come your way as a result of where you chose to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha compared the whole situation of staying in saṃsāra, like being in the house that the roof's on fire, and it's collapsing bit by bit, and it will crush you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he compared enlightenment to leaving that environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't compare enlightenment to repairing the roof beams, or re-roofing the tiles.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is usually what people want dhamma to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to fix my life so nothing bothers me, but also I can still stay in the house.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma takes you out of your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overcomes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, you leave the house that is on fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not you repair it or extinguish the fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You leave the dangerous environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or choose not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can't complain when you get burnt.
[SPEAKER_00]: A little bit, a bit more, and then eventually, when the whole roof starts coming down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, most of the time, it's like, you do the dhamma, so you can get back to what you were...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I do the dhamma as a way of, kind of, psychological psychotherapy, dealing with things that currently bother me, but only so that I can return to things that don't bother me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that whether there are things bothering you or not bothering you, either way, you're affected by things, and that's where the problem is.